So today's דף daf is כ״ב chaf bet (22). We're a little
behind. We pick up on כ״א עמוד ב׳ chaf alef amud bet
in the גמרא. gemara. We're now switching gears. We are in a
discussion about how many transgressions you can transgress in one act.
First a short line in the משנה mishna about somebody, which is
something we've seen before, that if somebody is doing something throughout an
entire day, it's considered one long process. He doesn't get multiple lashes
because the warning only came before once. But if there was a
warning before each successive act, like a נזיר nazir who's drinking wine,
then he would get lashes for each one. But
so the warning would set to divide them into separate acts. And
then it says similarly if somebody is wearing שעטנז shaatnez and he's
taking off and putting on his clothes, it's still only one set
of lashes if there's one warning. But if there's warnings before each
undressing and dressing, then it would be multiple. All right, so let's
see what the גמרא gemara says about that.
So we'll read it with the parentheses, or there's a version on
the side. אמר רב ביבי אמר רב אסי לא פושט ולא לובש
ממש אלא אפילו, Amar Rav Bibi amar Rav Assi lo poshet velo
lovesh mammash ela afilu, that's the way we have, אפילו מכניס ומוציא
בית הצואר וכלי שלו. afilu machnis vemotzi beit hatzavar ukli shelo. Even
if you didn't, the idea of what's multiple acts and multiple lashes
if you had a warning between each one is you don't need
to actually completely strip the garment. You just need it to be
a new act of partially putting on. So if like here you're
wearing your jacket here, so even if you just like took out
the arm and then put it back on, you like the visual
demonstration except my watch is getting caught, that's a new act of
putting on. Partially off and partially on. Okay, that that's sufficient. מחוי
רב אחא
בריה דרב איקא עולי ואפוקי. Machvei Rav Acha brei deRav Ika yulei
veafukei.
So Rav Acha the son of Rav Ika sort of demonstrated or
indicated going in and going out, which basically means the way the
ריב״ן Rivan explains it, it means no, I don't agree completely taking
it off and putting it back on. רב אשי אמר אפילו לא
שהה. Rav Ashi amar afilu lo shahah. Rav Ashi is most radical.
אפילו לא שהה אלא כדי לפשוט וללבוש חייב, afilu lo shahah ela
kedei lifshot velilvosh chayav, which I don't know how he reads that
in the משנה. mishna. But he says wearing and putting on are
different acts. Right, so if the איסור issur is לא ילבש כלאים,
lo yilbash kilayim, בגד כלאים שעטנז, beged kilayim shaatnez, you know, לא
יעלה עליך, lo yaaleh alecha, לא תלבש שעטנז, lo tilbash shaatnez,
so wearing does not mean putting on. Right, you put on your
clothes but right now I'm wearing my clothes. So he says if
you're even the fact that you are just leaving them on and
you have the time to take it off and put it on
again, that's considered an act of continued wearing. So if there's, I
mean you need the extra act of warning. Somebody warned me don't
put on this jacket, it's שעטנז, shaatnez, and I say I don't
care and I put it on. Okay, that's one set of lashes.
Then he says don't keep on wearing it, you're wearing שעטנז, shaatnez,
and I said I don't care and I keep on wearing it.
That makes it a second act. But he says not just the
wearing, it's like it's some interesting middle position because there needs to
be the potential, the amount of time that I could have taken
it off and put it back on and that's like a new
putting back on. So it's a little strange idea. If it was
just the idea that wearing is the act, then you wouldn't need
this amount of time to remove it and put it back on,
right? Maybe you would need the amount of time to remove it.
You would say the choice not to remove it is a choice
to continue wearing. That I would understand. So since I had the
chance to remove it and I didn't, I'm choosing to continue wearing.
But he says no, you also need the opportunity, theoretical opportunity to
take it off and put it on. It sounds like he is
defining the act as an act of putting on, not just an
act of wearing. And as such it's a little funny that he
imagined it to happen like theoretically even if it's not happening in
practice. Okay, yes.
Could you extend that maybe to all kinds of acts, right? That
every time a person gives a warning and expects that you're still
doing
this, that you
count it as another act.
Right, so let's say the נזיר nazir is drinking, drinking and you
say don't drink, it's forbidden, and he says I don't care and
he does it without choking or whatever and he keeps on drinking.
Right, you don't need like the picking up of the cup, right?
I agree, and because that's an act of drinking, it's not an
act of like picking up of a cup. Right, so here too
you could have said it's an act of warning, but then of
wearing. But I don't understand the amount of time that you need.
It's only he gets lashes when he could have taken it off
and put it back on. If again, if he would have said
it's the amount of time you need to take it off, then
you could say the choice not to take it off when you
had that time is a choice to continue wearing, right? But because
he can't just say I transgress in a second, you gotta give
me a chance to do something about it. Right, but the fact
that he says no, you must take it off and he's it
looks like he's conceptualizing it as a virtual putting on. Right, so
that's I think a particular חידוש. chidush. And that's I think a
question of how to define the act. Is it the putting on
or is it the no, if you look at the פסוק, pasuk,
first of all like to be לובש lovesh means to wear, not
to put on, especially the other פסוק pasuk where there's בגד כלאים
שעטנז לא, beged kilayim shaatnez lo, well maybe not, maybe that's the
difference. לא יעלה עליך, lo yaaleh alecha, so not you know go
up on you, that maybe does more suggest an act. to put
on, not to wear. So anyway, it's a very interesting middle position,
okay? Okay, so now let's take a look at the at the
next line. יש חורש תלם אחד. Yesh choresh telem echad.
Okay, so there's a person, this is now going to the second
part of the משנה mishnah
that it's somebody can be, you know, dig one furrow and transgress
eight prohibitions. Of course, the last two had nothing to do with
the furrow, which is what חנניה בן חכינאי Chananya ben Chakinai responded
back, they had to do with the fact that you happened to
be in a cemetery. So אמר רב ינאי, Amar Rav Yannai, בחבורה
נמנו וגמרו, Bechabura nimnu vegamru, in the sort of gathering, in the,
so the ריב״ן Rivan says, if you look at the ריב״ן, Rivan,
he winds down in the from the wide lines here, the line
under גמרא, Gemara, he says, נראה לי יום אסיפה או יום ועד
היה להם שקראו חבורה, Nireli yom asifa o yom vaad haya lahem
shekaru chabura, or some days that they all got together, a יום
עיון, yom iyun, okay? On the day, on anyway, on that day
what the community got together, the of learners got together, we took
a vote and we concluded,
החופר בכלאים לוקה, Hachofer bekilayim loke, that the prohibition of planting כלאים,
kilayim, okay, לא תזרע כרמך כלאים, Lo tizra karmicha kilayim, it's about
זורע, zoreya, that if you cover the seeds with dirt, that's like
you planted them, but that's like you put the seed in the,
the seed in the dirt, and that's a form of doing something
that gets the seed to grow, getting it covered with dirt, so
even though you didn't put the seed down, that's a form of
planting כלאים kilayim and you get lashes. אמר להם רבי יוחנן, Amar
lahem Rabi Yochanan, רבי יוחנן Rabi Yochanan said, לאו משנתנו היא זו?
Lav mishnateinu hi zo? I don't understand your big חידוש, chiddush, it's
implicit in our משנה. mishnah. Our משנה mishnah said, יש חורש תלם
אחד וחייב עליו משום שמונה לאוין, Yesh choresh telem echad vechayav alav
mishum shemoneh lavin, you can dig one furrow and get five lashes.
החורש בשור וחמור ומוקדשין וכלאים בכרם, Hachoresh b'shor vachamor u'mookdashin vekilayim b'kerem,
one of the lashes is because of the fact that you have
mixed seeds here, you have כלאים kilayim in the vineyard. So האי
חורש דמחייב משום כלאים היכי משכחת לה? Hai choresh demichayev mishum kilayim
heichi mishkachat la? So what's the idea that making a furrow you're
חייב chayav for כלאים? kilayim? Like if you, you're not חייב chayav
for making a furrow, right? That's not planting of a seed. So
what how's the furrow a way of transgressing כלאים? kilayim? So לאו
דמכסי בהדי דאזיל? Lav demichaseh behadi de'azil? The only way to explain
it is that as you're making the furrow, the dirt that you're
up-turning covers a seed and it's a form of planting the seed.
So you see, so it's already implicit in the משנה. mishnah. אמר
ליה, Amar lei, so he said back to him, אי לאו דדלינא
לך חספא
מי משכחת מרגניתא תותיה? Ei lav de'dalina lach chaspa mi mishkachat marganita
tutei? Had I not lifted up for you the pottery shard, you
never would have found the pearl hiding underneath it. Okay, yes, once
I told you this idea that it's a form of planting, you
were able to go ahead and now look with new eyes at
the משנה mishnah and see, oh, that's what's going on in the
משנה, mishnah, that's of course it's פשט! pshat! But you know, it's
so so true, like you know, they say the best, you know
you've come up to the real פשט, pshat, like the real explanation
of something, if after you've said it, it's obvious. Okay, of course
it's true, that's obvious! But before you said it, it wasn't obvious
at all. Okay, so that's what he said, yeah, very nice רבי
יוחנן, Rabi Yochanan, you're telling me it's obvious, it's obvious now that
I said it, now that you know, okay, had I not lifted
up this, you know, via the pottery shard, you never would have
found this pearl. It's a great line. Anyway, אמר ליה ריש לקיש
לרבי יוחנן, Amar lei Reish Lakish le'Rabi Yochanan, so ריש לקיש Reish
Lakish said to רבי יוחנן, Rabi Yochanan, אי לאו דקלסך
גברא רבא, Ei lav de'kalsach gavra raba, had this great man not
praised you, like he praised you by saying... it's a funny form
of praise, I guess he praised you that you found the pearl
after I, yeah, after I loosed the bottle cap, then you were
able to, after I lifted it up. But the point is, by
his response, it's clear that he agrees that that is פשט pshat
in the משנה. mishnah. You said it was in the משנה mishnah
and he said of course, you found the pearl, so he agrees
that that's פשט pshat in the משנה. mishnah. Had he not said
that that was פשט pshat in the
משנה, mishnah, הוה אמינא, hava amina, I would have said משנתנו מני
רבי עקיבא היא, mishnateinu manei Rabi Akiva hi, there's a different explanation
of the משנה. mishnah. Why does our משנה mishnah say that you
get lashes for planting, you know, a כלאים, kilayim, if all you
did was made a furrow? It's רבי עקיבא, Rabi Akiva, דתניא, detanya,
we learned in the ברייתא, braita, המנכש והמחפה בכלאים לוקה. Hamenakesh ve'hamichapeh
be'kilayim loke.
If somebody weeds or covers up dirt of a seed for כלאים,
kilayim, he gets lashes. רבי עקיבא אומר, Rabi Akiva omer, רבי עקיבא
Rabi Akiva said, אף המקיים, Af hamekayem,
even if you don't do anything, even if you just let them,
here similar to the idea of letting the שעטנז shatnez garment remain
on you, actually it's just interesting, it occurs to me both of
them are forms of כלאים, kilayim, right? A mixture. So then we
have letting the mixed, the garment of wool and linen stay on
you, even if you just let the כלאים kilayim stay in your
vineyard, you transgress. Now, it's all very nice to say that's a
form of transgressing, why you get lashes is a little bizarre, right?
Whatever happened to a לאו שאין בו מעשה? lav she'ein bo maaseh?
We actually did, should have raised that earlier when we discussed, you
know, רב אשי, Rav Ashi, why is it considered an act, you're
just standing around with the garment on you, right? So why do
you get lashes? I mean, do you say that having, wearing something
is active? I have my garment on me and I'm awake and
therefore it's considered I'm an act of wearing? Is it because I
originally did the act, you know, when I first put it on,
and therefore it's like I'm doing the act again? Right, we never
really discussed in that statement about wearing the שעטנז, shatnez, why is
it an act, an active? Fine, it's a transgression, but why is
it active to get lashes? So here, that's certainly the same question
for רבי עקיבא. Rabi Akiva. The גמרא Gemara does not explain. or
why it's considered an act and why you get lashes, but anyway,
but you do transgress just by leaving the seeds around. מאי טעמא
דרבי עקיבא? Mai ta'ama de'Rabbi Akiva? How does he know it's a
transgression just to leave it? דתניא, detanya, we saw in a ברייתא,
Braisa, שדך לא תזרע כלאים, Sadchecha lo tizra kilayim, כמה לא תזרע
כלאים. Kama lo tizra kilayim. אין לי אלא זורע, Ein li ela
zore'ah, I only know if he plants. מקיים מנין, Mekayem minayin, how
do you know even if he just let the seeds remain? תלמוד
לומר כלאים שדך לא. Talmud lomar kilayim sadchecha lo. Okay, because the
פסוק pasuk is, what's
the פסוק? pasuk? בהמתך לא
תרביע
כלאים שדך
לא תזרע
כלאים.
Behemtecha lo tarbiya kilayim
sadchecha lo
tizra kilayim. So it's, so if you emphasize תזרע, tizra, you're
not going to get just leaving it around, okay, because you weren't
זורע zore'ah because it has to be זריעה. zeriyah. So what we
do is we read the פסוק pasuk like this, okay, we take
the end of the last one, כלאים שדך לא. Kilayim sadchecha lo.
Don't just allow there to be כלאים kilayim in your field, okay,
and we sort of bracket this verb here. So it's just allowing
it to be in your field and therefore you transgress. כלאים שדך
לא. Kilayim sadchecha lo. Okay, so now, okay, so A, that's all
very nice, so you transgress, but there's a couple problems. Number one,
how did, why do you get lashes? It was passive. Number two,
it's still a little funny because the משנה mishna says that you're
חייב chayav for making the furrow. According to this reading of it
that it's not, has nothing to do with making of the furrow.
The furrow had nothing to do with why you got lashes. You
got lashes because you did let the כלאים kilayim stay in your
field, right? It's not related to making the furrow. Maybe those two
questions answer one another. Maybe the idea is that the making of
the furrow is not a planting of כלאים, kilayim, right? We're saying
I could have said that that covering it with dirt isn't seen
as a form of planting. It's not a planting of כלאים, kilayim,
but it certainly shows that you are, want to keep the כלאים
kilayim in your field. You understand? It's like if the כלאים kilayim
are in my field and I'm in the house and doing nothing
about it, fine, I'm totally passive. If I go out to the
field and I actually do stuff, I build a fence around it
to keep the animals out, I weed it, I make furrows, I
am actively showing, I might not be planting the כלאים, kilayim, but
I'm actively demonstrating that I want the כלאים kilayim there. Okay, so
maybe those two questions answer one another and that's why you get
lashes. And the גמרא Gemara is saying but I wouldn't have to
say that it's a form of planting. I could have read the
משנה mishna that it's רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and it's just a
form of showing that you want to keep the כלאים kilayim there.
All right, by the way, it's a little funny because we made
this big חידוש chiddush of רב ינאי Rav Yannai that covering is
like planting and here this ברייתא Braisa says המנכש והמכפה לוקה, Hamenakes
vehamechapeh lokeh, you get lashes. So it sounds like it's already in
the ברייתא, Braisa, the idea that covering is a form of, is
a form of planting. Anyway, we'll just bracket that. So now the
גמרא Gemara says like this, אמר ליה
עולא
לרב נחמן. Amlei Ula l'Rav Nachman. So עולא Ula said to רב
נחמן, Rav Nachman, דילקי נמי משום זורע ביום טוב. dilki nami mishum
zore'ah b'Yom Tov. Fine, that's the end. So we've introduced the idea
that maybe you get lashes just for wearing שעטנז. shaatnez. Why is
that considered active and not passive, I don't know. You get lashes
for covering כלאים kilayim with dirt, either because that is a form
of planting, because the covering with dirt is like putting the seed
in the dirt, or because it is a for רבי עקיבא, Rabbi
Akiva, it's a form, a way of showing that you're happy that
the כלאים kilayim is there and you want to keep it
there. Okay, so now we're done with those particular cases. Now we
ask, why did the משנה mishna limit itself to just eight? I
could have come up with other cases. And not only, and there's
two ways of getting other cases. One is let's just come up
with complete new עבירות aveiros to try to stick into making a
furrow. But the other is even within the context that the גמרא
Gemara was, that the משנה mishna was talking, there seems to have
been more עבירות aveiros that I could have counted. Let's take a
look.
So אמר ליה עולא לרב נחמן. Amlei Ula l'Rav Nachman. So עולא
Ula said to רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, דילקי נמי משום זורע ביום
טוב. dilki nami mishum zore'ah b'Yom Tov. I don't get it. We
said that you're making a furrow on יום טוב Yom Tov and
we said that you're planting כלאים, kilayim, so you're also planting on
יום טוב, Yom Tov, right? That makes a lot of sense. It's
right there in the משנה. mishna. You're planting כלאים kilayim because the
furrow is a form of planting and you're making a furrow on
יום טוב, Yom Tov, so you're also planting on יום טוב. Yom
Tov. So אמר ליה, amlei, תנא ושייר. tana v'shiyer. All right, it
was an incomplete list. אמר ליה, amlei, תנא קתני שמונה ואת אמרת
תנא ושייר? Tana katani shmona v'at amart tana v'shiyer? No, the whole
point of the תנא tana is to give you a lot of
עבירות aveiros and it explicitly says eight. And in the very description,
it's not saying let why isn't, doesn't add a, like a new
scenario. It's not a new scenario. In the exact same scenario it's
describing, there's nine, not eight, because you're making a furrow on יום
טוב Yom Tov and if there are seeds there and you're planting
the seeds, you're also planting on יום טוב. Yom Tov. It's a
pretty darn good question. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, so says
רבא, Rava, יש חילוק מלאכות בשבת ואין חילוק. yesh chiluk melachos b'Shabbos
v'ein chiluk. By שבת, Shabbos, every different מלאכה melacha is considered a
different עבירה, aveirah, and the proof being that if somebody forgets it's
שבת Shabbos and does all the מלאכות, melachos, they bring thirty-nine קרבנות,
korbanos, okay? Each one is considered a distinct עבירה. aveirah. By יום
טוב, Yom Tov, the different מלאכות melachos are not distinct עבירות. aveiros.
It's doing a furrow and planting is like doing two furrows. There's
no distinct identity to it. It's just you broke יום טוב, Yom
Tov, okay? But it's not like it has a different identity. You
were בורר, borer, you were אופה, ofeh, you were... you know, you
were בונה. boneh. No, you broke יום טוב. Yom Tov. All right,
and therefore making a furrow and planting, we might have as well
just have said you made two furrows. All right, and since it's
all presumably in one state of being warned, so if it's in
one state of being warned, right, you don't get two sets of
lashes for making two furrows. Somebody said, don't make a furrow on
יום טוב, Yom Tov, and you said, I don't care, and you
made two furrows, you get one set of lashes. So if somebody
said, don't make a furrow on יום טוב Yom Tov and don't
plant on יום טוב, Yom Tov, and you said, I don't care,
and you made a furrow and you planted, you only get one
set of lashes. It's a little surprising, right? But it's basically like
the person just said, don't break יום טוב, Yom Tov, and you
said, I don't care, and you broke יום טוב Yom Tov twice,
okay? So we don't conceptualize it as two different עבירות. aveiros. We
conceptualize it as one עבירה aveirah of breaking יום טוב, Yom Tov,
so you broke יום טוב Yom Tov twice with one warning, that's
only one set of lashes. All right, so that's a very interesting
concept.
אמר ליה אדא תהא, Amar lei Ada Tehei, so Ada says like,
oh, that is like a good, like it's a little hard, like
it's a... it's like a little idiomatic expression, but it basically is
like, oh, that's a good explanation, okay? This is the way it
should be. איתיביה אביי, Eiseivieh Abaye, and now אביי Abaye however challenged
it, even though we seem to have a very nice satisfying answer,
אביי Abaye challenged this idea that you don't have a distinct identity
for different מלאכות melachos on יום טוב. Yom Tov. ואין חילוק מלאכות
ביום טוב? V'ein chiluk melachos b'Yom Tov? Are you telling me there's
no distinct identity? דתנן, De-tanan, we taught in the משנה, mishna, he
has another case of multiple עבירות, aveiros, okay? המבשל גיד
בחלב ביום
טוב, Ha-mevashel gid be-chalav b'Yom Tov, so you take a גיד הנשה,
gid hanasheh, okay, which is like the part of the sinew that
you're not allowed to eat. This משנה mishna assumes that it's treated
like meat. You cook it with milk. Okay, so how many עבירות
aveiros are you doing? You're cooking meat and milk, that's one. It's
going to be one of these other things about listing how many
עבירות aveiros you can get. You do it on יום טוב, Yom
Tov, that's two. ואכלו, V'achalo, and then you ate it. Now by
eating it, what did you transgress? You transgressed eating בשר בחלב, basar
be-chalav, that's three, eating a גיד הנשה, gid hanasheh, that's four. So
לוקה חמש. lokei chamesh. Now five, how did you get five? So
let's take a look. אוכל גיד, Ochel gid, you ate a גיד
הנשה, gid hanasheh, ולוקה משום אוכל גיד, v'lokei mishum ochel gid, ולוקה
משום מבשל ביום טוב, v'lokei mishum mevashel b'Yom Tov, you cooked on
יום טוב, Yom Tov, okay, oh maybe we didn't mention... well we
did mention that. שלא לצורך, She-lo le-tzorech, you cooked on יום טוב
Yom Tov without a purpose because you cooked something that you're not
allowed to eat, okay? Like normally you should say, what do you
mean? You're allowed to cook on יום טוב. Yom Tov. But you're
not allowed to cook בשר בחלב basar be-chalav or גיד הנשה, gid
hanasheh, that's something you're not allowed to eat. So cooking without a
purpose is two.
ולוקה משום מבשל גיד בחלב, v'lokei mishum mevashel gid be-chalav, cooking the
גיד gid with milk as meat and milk, ולוקה משום אוכל בשר
בחלב, v'lokei mishum ochel basar be-chalav, eating בשר בחלב. basar be-chalav. So
those four were obvious. Which is number five? ולוקה משום, v'lokei mishum,
so drum roll please, here's number five: הבערה. havarah. You made the
fire in order to cook. Okay, so now two of those five
are יום טוב Yom Tov violations: making a fire and cooking without
a purpose. So you see that they're considered separate עבירות aveiros on
יום טוב, Yom Tov, right? Because you get two separate sets of
lashes. ואי איתא, Ve-im issa, and if it's true that on יום
טוב Yom Tov we don't consider different מלאכות melachos to be different
עבירות, aveiros, so משום הבערה לא מחייב, mishum havarah lo mechayav, you
should not get a separate set of lashes for making the fire.
דהא חייב ליה משום בישולו, De-ha chayiv lei mishum bishulo, you already
got a set of lashes for cooking. It's an excellent question. That
makes it clear that you conceptualize them as separate עבירות. aveiros.
So the גמרא's Gemara answer is: fine, let's change the
ברייתא braisa or the משנה, mishna, excuse me. אפיק הבערה ועייל גיד
הנשה של נבילה. Afik havarah v'ayeil gid hanasheh של neveilah. Fine, take
out... so take out the idea, let's say it is not because
of...
the reason you get lashes is not because of making the fire.
The reason you get lashes is we forgot to mention that this
גיד הנשה gid hanasheh was also of a נבילה neveilah animal, an
animal that died that wasn't שחוטה. shechted. So you get another set
of lashes for eating a נבילה. neveilah. Okay, all of this by
the way assumes that you treat a גיד הנשה gid hanasheh like
meat. There's a whole debate, you might not treat it like meat,
maybe you're not חייב chayiv for בשר בחלב, basar be-chalav, maybe you're
not חייב chayiv for eating it as the meat of a נבילה.
neveilah. It's a sinew, it's not the flesh. Okay, but this assumes
we're treating it like it is the flesh. Okay, so that's how
we get five, not for making the fire.
So the גמרא Gemara says: wait a minute, והתני רבי חייא, v'hata-ni
Rabbi Chiya, but didn't רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya teach a ברייתא braisa
to explain this משנה? mishna? And רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya teaches, לוקה
שתים על אכילתו ושלש על בישולו. lokeh shtayim al achilaso v'shalosh al
bishulo. Two of the lashes are for the eating: you ate בשר
בחלב basar be-chalav and you ate גיד הנשה, gid hanasheh, and three
of the lashes are for the cooking part of the... process. Okay,
and you, you want to make three of them about eating, you
wanted to add one for eating נבלה. neveilah. והשתא ve-hashta according to
your way of reading, it's שלש על אכילתו הוא חייב. shalosh al
achilato hu chayav. So you can't do that. It's clear that only
two of them are eating עבירות: aveiros: בשר בחלב basar be-chalav and
גיד הנשה, gid hanashe, and three are cooking, relate to the cooking.
So we have cooking on יום טוב Yom Tov without a purpose,
cooking בשר בחלב. basar be-chalav. It seems like the only possible third
one is the making of the fire. So אלא ela fine, no,
here's how we're going to deal with it. אתי כפרה, ati kavara,
fine, it is about the fire, but it's not about making a
fire on יום טוב. Yom Tov. It's not that that was the
problem. ועצי אשירה. ve-atzei asheirah. The problem was you made a fire
with עבודה זרה avodah zarah wood. We forgot to mention that. Of
course that's, that's clearly not פשט. pshat. The משנה Mishnah does not
talk about using עבודה זרה avodah zarah wood, it just talks about
this act of making this cooking this thing on יום טוב. Yom
Tov. But that's how we're answering it. Make it that you use
עבודה זרה avodah zarah wood. ואזהרתיה מהכא, ve-ahzarteih mei-hacha, and the prohibition
is from here: ולא ידבק בידך מאומה מן החרם. ve-lo yidbak be-yadcha
me-umah min hacherem. Nothing from the stuff under the ban can stick
to your hands, meaning you can't derive any benefit from things related
to עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. So that's how you get five. אמר
ליה רב אחא בריה דרבא לרב אשי, amar leih Rav Acha breih
de-Rava le-Rav Ashi, so רב אחא בריה דרבא Rav Acha breih de-Rava
said to רב אשי, Rav Ashi, ולילקי נמי משום לא תביא תועבה
אל ביתך. ve-lilki nami mishum lo tavi to-evah el beitecha.
If you're dealing with עבודה זרה avodah zarah wood, then there should
be another set of lashes, not just getting הנאה, hana-ah, but actually
taking possession of it. Don't bring it to your house means don't
possess it. Okay, so clearly we're not talking about עבודה זרה avodah
zarah wood, you know, besides the fact that it's obviously completely not
in the משנה. Mishnah. אלא הכא במאי עסקינן, ela hacha be-mai askinan,
what are we talking about? שכבישלו בעצי
הקדש. she-kevishlo be-atzei hekdesh. Again not in the משנה, Mishnah, okay, but
still that's what we're going to say. You used woods that were
sanctified. ואזהרתיה מהכא, ve-ahzarteih mei-hacha, ואשריהם תשרפון באש לא תעשון כן להשם
אלקיכם. ve-ashei-reihom tisrefun ba-eish lo taasun kein la-Hashem Elokeichem. You should destroy
the trees of עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, don't do this to God.
So it's destroying הקדש. hekdesh. It's interesting, they could have said you're
benefiting from הקדש. hekdesh. תוספות Tosafot asks why it didn't say that.
Okay, but anyway that's how you get the fifth. Now that is
a very weak read, okay? The משנה Mishnah obviously clearly seems to
be that the problem revolved around the fact that it was יום
טוב Yom Tov and בשר בחלב basar be-chalav and גיד הנשה. gid
hanashe. So the simple sense of that משנה Mishnah is that different
מלאכות melachos on יום טוב Yom Tov are considered different עבירות. aveiros.
But this is in a, but then we have a problem with
our משנה. Mishnah. Our משנה Mishnah should have mentioned both planting and,
and plowing. So we're going to go with the idea, and it's
a very interesting idea, that on יום טוב, Yom Tov, on שבת
Shabbos you view different מלאכות melachos as different types of עבירות. aveiros.
Whereas
by שבת Shabbos we're never talking about lashes because שבת Shabbos is
חייב מיתה, chayeiv misah, we're talking about different קרבנות. korbanot. But by
יום טוב Yom Tov where we talk about lashes, we view it
all as just different ways of breaking יום טוב. Yom Tov. It's
not different types of עבירות, aveiros, it's just you broke יום טוב
Yom Tov this way, you broke יום טוב Yom Tov that way,
at the end of the day it's one עבירה. aveirah. You broke
יום טוב. Yom Tov. I don't care if you made two furrows
or if you made a furrow and you planted. I don't care
if you cooked something you're not allowed to cook and you made
a fire or you just, or you just made two fires, okay?
Whatever it is, it's all just different ways of breaking יום טוב.
Yom Tov. That's what we're saying. So in order to make that
work with that משנה Mishnah over there by גיד הנשה, gid hanashe,
we say the problem there was a completely different one. It was
using a fire of הקדש hekdesh wood. That was the problem. But
אין הכי נמי, in hachi nami, two different ways of breaking יום
טוב Yom Tov is only one set of lashes. Okay, so that's
the conclusion there, very interesting and important idea. Okay, now we're going
to say that was just the straightforward question. In the very scenario
of the משנה, Mishnah, there seems to be two ways of breaking
יום טוב, Yom Tov, why did our משנה Mishnah only give you
one set of lashes? Now we're going to say, hey, why didn't
we just change the scenario a little bit and we can get
a lot more עבירות aveiros thrown into the case of the משנה.
Mishnah. Okay, and you get a sense here that the גמרא Gemara
is just having a little bit of fun. So let's take a
look. Okay. מתקיף לה רב הושעיא, matkif lah Rav Hoshaya, so now
רב הושעיא Rav Hoshaya asks, ולחשוב נמי הזורע בנחל איתן. ve-lachshov nami
hazorea be-nachal eitan. So that's pretty straightforward. Since we're talking that the
problem is plowing and planting, I could have given you a way
to have made another forbidden plant. Why didn't you just say you
were planting in the, in the ואדי wadi of
איתן, eitan, right, which is where you do the whole, what do
you call it, the עגלה ערופה, eglah arufah, you're not supposed to
plant in the ואדי wadi where you do that whole ritual of
the עגלה ערופה, eglah arufah, okay? And that's a negative prohibition. So
what, we could have given that scenario, that would have added another
set of lashes. ואזהרתיה מהכא אשר לא יעבד בו ולא יזרע, ve-ahzarteih
mei-hacha asher lo ye-aveid bo ve-lo yizarei-a, cannot be worked and cannot
be planted. Since the whole problem here is planting, there's other עבירות
aveiros you can throw on. Okay. מתקיף לה רב חנינא, matkif lah
Rav Chanina, רב חנינא Rav Chanina asks, ולחשוב נמי המוחק את השם
בהליכתו. ve-lachshov nami hamochek et hashem be-halichato. Now we, so the question
about the ואדי wadi of איתן, eitan, that was straightforward. That was
an act of planting that was forbidden, okay, or act of working
the land, so plowing also. But now we seem to be just
having fun. It says, wow, why don't we say the following? As
you're doing your plowing, you're also erasing a name of God that
happens to be written on something, like what? Like it's completely incidental
and unrelated. I don't know, maybe imagine that your plow is running
over some piece of parchment and your plow is scraping out the
name of God. But now obviously it's getting to be a little
absurd. Okay. ועקרתם מהכא ואיבדתם את שמם מן המקום ההוא לא תעשון
כן להשם אלוקיכם Veakartem mehacha veibadtem et shemam min hamakom hahu lo
taasun ken l'Hashem Elokeichem like we just said before. So maybe your
plow is like destroying something with God's name on it. Okay. ולא
תעשון, Velo taasun, okay. מתקיף לה רבי אבהו, Matkif lei Rabbi Abbahu,
heck, once we're at that, doing that, ולחשוב נמי הקוצץ את בהרתו.
velachshov nami hakoitzes as baharto. You're not allowed to cut off a
leprous sort of spot that you have. הישמר בנגע הצרעת. Hishamer benega
hatzaraas. So what if he... imagine as you're doing your plowing, you
have a little razor and you're
cutting some spot out of your skin or no, maybe what you
do is I say, 'Hey, David, you got that leprous spot, I'm
going to be plowing right here. Why don't you stick your arm
right in front of my plow, and I'll run my plow over
your arm in a way that it'll cut out your leprous spot?'
So you can really look like that. I had a teacher who
once said, 'Well, you know, this is what they did before they
had TV.' You know.
It's like, 'Oh, let's see what we can figure out here.' Okay.
So we're just, you know, clearly now we're going a little off
the rails. Okay. מתקיף לה אביי, Matkif lei Abaye, אביי Abaye asks,
ולחשוב נמי המזיח את החושן מעל האפוד. velachshov nami hamaziach es hachoshen
mei'al ha'ephod. You're not allowed to move the חושן, choshen, the breastplate,
from the אפוד ephod of the כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. So what
if the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol happens to be standing in my
way as I'm plowing and in my way of, and in my
going through with the plow, I bump into him and I cause
the חושן, choshen, the breastplate, to be removed from the
אפוד ephod there? Okay. והמסיר בדי ארון. Vahameisir badei aron. Let's say
somehow somebody brought the ארון, aron, you know, the
Lost Ark, like Indiana Jones is going through with the Lost Ark
that he had just recovered, okay, he got in the way of
my field and as I was plowing, I bumped into the staves
and I removed the staves. You know, you gotta get your humor
where you're gonna get it.
לא יסורו Lo yasuru ולא יזח החושן. veloi yizach hachoshen. Fine. Don't
remove the staves and don't remove the חושן. choshen. מתקיף לה רב
אשי, Matkif lei Rav Ashi, רב אשי Rav Ashi asks, ולחשוב נמי
החורש בעצי אשרה. velachshov nami hachoresh ba'atzei asheira. Okay, that's a little
bit more normal. Let's say you're using אשרה asheira wood, we mentioned
אשרה asheira before, עבודה זרה avoda zara wood, and they are making
up your plow. So you're benefiting, again, it's still not... you're, you
know, in your act of plowing, that is deriving benefit, and you're
benefiting from this
עבודה זרה avoda zara wood. ולא ידבק בידך מאומה מן החרם.
Veloi yidbak beyadecha m'uma
min hacherem. מתקיף לה רבינא, Matkif lei Ravina, רבינא Ravina asks, ולחשוב
נמי הקוצץ אילנות טובות. velachshov nami hakoitzetz ilanos toivos. Ah, that's maybe
not so bad. As you're plowing, in the way of your plow
are these nice good fruit trees, and you're cutting them down without
a purpose. Right, that's
בל תשחית. bal tashchis. Okay. The prohibition is כי ממנו תאכל ואותו
לא תכרות. ki mimenu sochel veoso loi sichros. Don't cut down a
fruit tree for no purpose. That's בל תשחית. bal tashchis. אמר ליה
רב זירא לרבי מני, Amar lei Rav Zeira l'Rabbi Mani, ולחשוב נמי
כגון דאמר שבועה שלא אחרוש ביום טוב. velachshov nami kegon de'amar shevua
shelo achrosh beyom tov. Okay, this is already like... not... all those
other things were almost completely incidental to the act of plowing. All
right, but now we're saying something more absurd. But now we're saying,
let's say a guy took an שבועה shevua not to plow. Okay,
that would be a way that in his act of plowing, he
would get another עבירה aveira because of the שבועה shevua that he
took. So we start by saying the שבועה shevua was not to
plow on יום טוב, Yom Tov, because you remember the scenario in
the משנה Mishnah was that it was
יום טוב. Yom Tov. So, התם לא חלה שבועה. hasam lo chala
shevua. No, no. If he said an שבועה shevua I won't plow
on יום טוב, Yom Tov, the שבועה shevua doesn't take effect. מושבע
ועומד מהר סיני, Mushba ve'omed me'har sinai, meaning he's already sworn and
standing from Mount Sinai, meaning he's already... you can't take a שבועה
shevua to do something that goes against, excuse me, that repeats what
the תורה Torah obligates you to do. Since the תורה Torah already
demands that you don't plow on יום טוב, Yom Tov, your שבועה
shevua not to plow on יום טוב Yom Tov does not take
effect. מושבע ועומד מהר סיני. Mushba ve'omed me'har sinai. אמר
ליה, Amar lei, fine, let's say it's a little different. כגון דאמר
שבועה שלא אחרוש בין בחול בין ביום טוב. Kegon de'amar shevua shelo
achrosh bein bechol bein beyom tov. He just takes a generic שבועה,
shevua, 'I won't plow at all'. Okay, and therefore, since דמיגו דחלה
שבועה בחול, demigo dechala shevua bechol, since that's effective on the weekday,
because the weekday he's allowed to plow, so his שבועה shevua not
to plow is effective on the weekday. If he plows on the
weekday he
violates. חלה עליה נמי ביום טוב. Chala alei nami beyom tov. This
is a principle that something that has a broader scope, even though
if it was a narrow it would be redundant and it wouldn't
take effect, if it has a broader scope, then it does take
effect even in the area that it's sort of duplicating. Okay. מידי
דאיתא בשאר... Midi de'isa beshe'ar... okay, so that's the answer. That's called
a principle of like איסור כולל. issur kolel. Okay, that if the
איסור issur was completely redundant, you're already prohibited on plowing of יום
טוב, Yom Tov, the שבועה shevua wouldn't take effect. Since now the
שבועה shevua is broader and it takes effect on a whole wider
range of things, it also takes effect on top of your יום
טוב Yom Tov obligations. Okay, so that's another way to get... it's
very interesting. Notice by the way that the גמרא Gemara here is
stopping and actually analyzing this discussion seriously. All the other suggestions, the
גמרא Gemara didn't make any comment, it just let it, you know,
it just went by. Because all the other ones were almost completely
incidental. little absurd and they were completely incidental. This is an example
of where we really have another prohibition that is about plowing, if
you took an oath about not to plow. So this, at least
we are trying to understand why it wasn't in the משנה. Mishna.
Okay, would you get two if it was that type of an
oath, then would there be a double punishment for that, יום טוב
Yontif and the oath?
Right, even though the תורה Torah had already
prohibited it, but because the oath was effective in other cases, it's
effective even on יום טוב. Yontif. So this is the one that
we're actually treating seriously because this is a real non-incidental type of
an עבירה. aveira. The other עבירות aveiros were incidental. And here we're
saying, so okay, why wasn't that listed in the משנה? Mishna? So
the גמרא's Gemara answer is מדי דאיתא בשאלה לא קתני. midei d'islei
b'sheila lo katani. We're not mentioning things in the משנה Mishna that
are not
absolute. Things that you could get out of if you were just
go ahead and do שאלה, sheila, meaning you'd ask a חכם, chochom,
you do התרת נדרים. hataras nedarim. But you go to a sage
and you'd say, had I known this, I never would have taken
this oath, and then he frees you from the oath. Okay, so
in our משנה Mishna we're talking about עבירות aveiros that are non-negotiable.
This one in theory you could get out of if you were
to go to a חכם, chochom, so that's why it's not listed
in the משנה. Mishna. גמרא Gemara says ולא? v'lo? Really, is that
really the case? והרי
הקדש. v'harei hekdesh. First of all, והרי הקדש, v'harei hekdesh, one of
the cases in the משנה Mishna was that the animal you were
using was sanctified. Well, sanctifying something is something you do by a
verbal act, and similar to making an oath, and it's something that
you could reverse. You could reverse the sanctity that you've given the
thing. So how come that's listed in the משנה Mishna even though
that is in theory reversible? So the גמרא Gemara says בבכור. b'bechor.
No, we're talking about the case of הקדש hekdesh was בכור, bechor,
was a firstborn animal. And a firstborn animal is not because of
your verbal sanctifying of it. That animal was sanctified regardless. So that's
again a non-negotiable type of a thing. So the גמרא Gemara says
והרי נזיר. v'harei nazir. How about the case of a נזיר? nazir?
It had a נזיר nazir in a cemetery. A נזיר nazir is
done through a verbal act. It's a type of similar to an
oath or a vow, and it can be reversed by doing התרת
נדרים. hataras nedarim. And that's in the משנה. Mishna.
So the גמרא Gemara says בנזיר שמשון. b'nazir Shimshon. It was the
שמשון Shimshon Nazirite that cannot be reversed. Now, what is נזיר שמשון
nazir Shimshon that cannot be reversed? So
you could say somebody just takes a oath and says, I accept
upon myself to be blah, and then he says to be a
נזיר שמשון. nazir Shimshon. Okay, but then why can't it be reversed?
Why is that some type of an oath or whatever, not oath,
but whatever, a הפלאה, haflaa, a speech act that's not reversible? So
the ריב"ן Rivon says the reason it's not reversible is because what
was the case by שמשון? Shimshon? Who decided that שמשון Shimshon would
be a נזיר? nazir? Anybody? The angel?
Well, what, the angel.
Right, the
angel came and said נזיר יהיה הילד, nazir yiheye hayeled, whatever, whatever
the פסוק... posuk... anyway. Okay, so it says oh, so if the
angel is
demanding, if it's from God that you be a נזיר, nazir, then
you didn't do it to yourself, you don't get an opportunity to
reverse it. So okay, what's that mean? That means the משנה Mishna
is talking about a case that there was another angel visitation? I
didn't know those things happened nowadays. It's a little bizarre to think
that there's this הלכה halachic category if an angel happens to have
this visitation and makes you into a נזיר, nazir, right, then it
can't be reversed. But that's what the ריב"ן Rivon says. I didn't
look if there are other explanations. You know, you could have said
it means that no, part of the quality of a נזיר שמשון
nazir Shimshon is even though you did it and you verbally said
that they're accepting upon themselves to be a נזיר שמשון, nazir Shimshon,
maybe one of the unique features of it is that it's not
reversible. Right, that would have been a natural thing to say. But
he doesn't like that. He says where did we ever hear that
something you did and you verbally accepted upon yourself you can't reverse?
It's a general principle that you could do התרת נדרים. hataras nedarim.
So he says we're talking about a case, the only case we're
talking about of נזיר שמשון nazir Shimshon is an angel came and
told you that you were going to be, you or your child
or whoever was going to be a נזיר. nazir. Yes.
Could it be something like what חנה Chana did for שמואל? Shmuel?
So he suggests that, he says maybe
it's the case of, but he doesn't mention the mother, but he
has maybe it's because the father decided it, you could say the
mother, mother was a bigger player in the שמשון Shimshon story than
the father. But then he says, but then at least in theory
the parent could also retract it. So it's not that it's not
retractable. Now you could have said, okay, but it's maybe it's not
retractable by the person who's the actual נזיר. nazir. Maybe in theory
it's retractable, but it's not retractable by that person. So there was
other explanations you could have said, right? You could have said what
Gloria said, which the ריב"ן Rivon suggests, that if it's accepted by
a parent, then at least it's not retractable by the child. It
might be retractable by the parent, but it's not by the child.
Or maybe the nature of נזיר שמשון, nazir Shimshon, if you say
that, one of the laws is you're not allowed to retract it.
Okay, but he says anyway we're talking about an angel. One way
or another way, that's the case in the משנה Mishna now we're
saying. Since we want to explain why the משנה Mishna didn't have
the case of שבועה. shvua. We're saying the משנה Mishnah doesn't deal
with things that are retractable. And therefore we're saying it's talking about
נזיר שמשון. Nazir Shimshon. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says: One minute,
נזיר שמשון בר איתמולי למיתי הוא? Nazir Shimshon bar itmulei lemeisei hu?
One of the unique features of נזיר שמשון, Nazir Shimshon, in addition
to that it's not retractable, is that it doesn't prohibit the נזיר
Nazir from coming in contact with the dead. Just read your story.
Go ahead and read the שמשון Shimshon story. He's killing a lot
of people. So one of the principles we have is that a
נזיר שמשון Nazir Shimshon can come in contact with the dead. Oh,
by the way, you know how on התרת נדרים Hataras Nedarim that
we do ערב ראש השנה, Erev Rosh Hashanah, we say when we
say that you're asking for התרה, Hatara, we say ואפילו, va'afillu, there's
different גרסאות. girsos. Some say ואפילו נזירות שמשון va'afillu Nezirus Shimshon and
some of the גרסאות girsos say חוץ מנזירות שמשון. chutz mi-Nezirus Shimshon.
Does anybody ever notice we mention נזירות שמשון Nezirus Shimshon in the
התרת נדרים? Hataras Nedarim? And part of that has to do with
this question: is נזירות שמשון Nezirus Shimshon something you're able to ask
התרת נדרים Hataras Nedarim for? So if you go look at your
נוסח nusach of התרת נדרים, Hataras Nedarim, you'll see נזיר שמשון Nazir
Shimshon mentioned explicitly. Okay, so גמרא Gemara says: אלא, ela, fine. Forget
it. Our משנה Mishnah does include things that are verbally retractable. Okay,
so then why didn't it not mention the case of the שבועה?
Shvuah? אלא האי תנא איסור כולל לית ליה, Ela hai tanna issur
kolel leis lei, because he doesn't hold of this idea that if
it's a bit- just because it took effect the שבועה Shvuah took
effect on the weekday, it also takes effect on יום טוב. Yom
Tov. That's איסור כולל. issur kolel. If it has a broader effect
on areas that- that it was able to take effect, it takes
effect even on this redundant area of יום טוב. Yom Tov. No,
he says our תנא Tanna doesn't hold with that. Our תנא Tanna
holds that even if the guy took an oath not to plow
ever, it only transgresses on the weekday. He doesn't transgress on יום
טוב, Yom Tov, because on יום טוב Yom Tov he was already
forsworn at הר סיני. Har Sinai. Okay, so that's why the שבועה
Shvuah case is not in our משנה. Mishnah. אמר רבי אושעיא. Amar
Rabbi Oshaya. Okay, so now we're done listing the cases in one
type of a plowing you can do multiple sins. Okay, with interesting
discussions of איסור כולל issur kolel and interesting discussions of what I
thought was particularly interesting whether יום טוב, Yom Tov, different מלאכות melachos
on יום טוב Yom Tov are different sins. Now we have what
might be one of the most bizarre lines in the גמרא. Gemara.
The- you know, the ריב"ן Rivan says he doesn't understand it at
all. He says דבר תימה הוא. davar teima hu. So here it
is. אמר רבי אושעיא: Amar Rabbi Oshaya: המרביע שור פסולי המוקדשים לוקה.
hamarbia shor pesulei hamukdashim loke. Most don't have the גרסא שנים. girsa
shnayim. If somebody crossbreeds an animal that is פסולי המוקדשים pesulei hamukdashim
you get lashes. Now crossbreeds with what? And the answer is even
with another one of the same type. You have a cow. That's
all it is. It's a cow. But this cow was sanctified as
a קרבן korban and then it got a blemish and then you
redeemed it. Okay, big deal. Well the תורה Torah says that you
can- you have to treat this a little bit like הקדש hekdesh
because you're not allowed to work it and you're not allowed to,
you know, shear it and so on. On the other hand, it's
not הקדש hekdesh because you can slaughter it and eat it outside
the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, you can make it טמא. tamei. So
it has like a little bit a quasi a tri- like a
vestigial הקדש hekdesh status. Okay, so what רב אושעיא Rav Oshaya is
assuming is because this is both a חולין chullin and הקדש hekdesh
mixed together as if it's like a little bit of both, more
חולין chullin than הקדש, hekdesh, it's like
it's two animals mixed together. And therefore if you crossbreed it with
another one just like it, it's like you're crossbreeding two animals. You-
really you're just mating two cows. But this is a הקדש-חולין hekdesh-chullin
cow and this is a הקדש-חולין hekdesh-chullin cow and you're mating them
so you're like mixing הקדש hekdesh with חולין chullin and that's like
crossbreeding. Which is like what? That's crazy. Let's say I just take
an animal that's a קרבן korban and I crossbreed it with an
animal that's חולין. chullin. Are you going to say that's כלאיים? kilayim?
I mean, really, like what- what sense does that make, right? Anyway
that's what he's saying. But wait, it gets better. He says: אמר
רבי יצחק, Amar Rabbi Yitzchak, so רבי יצחק Rabbi Yitzchak does this
one better. המנהיג בשור פסולי המוקדשים לוקה. hammanhig beshor pesulei hamukdashim loke.
You don't even need another animal. Once you're saying that this is
like two animals mixed together, okay, let's say you go ahead and
you just take this cow and you just have it draw a
load. Ah, you just did כלאיים. kilayim. You had two ani- two
animals drawing a load. You're not allowed to like- you're like שור
וחמור, shor v'chamor, right, ox and a donkey draw a load together
two separate animals. So this animal in itself is two separate animals.
שהרי גוף אחד הוא ועשאו כתוב כשני גופים. Sheharei guf echad hu
v'asa'o kasuv kishnei gufim.
It's one body and the תורה Torah made it like two bodies.
Which is like insane. And let's say you do something else, let's
say you sort of said I מקדיש, makdish, I make half of
this animal הקדש. hekdesh. Okay,
you know, would you say that that's also the same? But anyway
it's one animal. How can you say that it's like you're, you
know, that like you're mixing two breeds of animals or whatever? So
the- the ריב"ן Rivan doesn't understand this. תוספות Tosafos and the רמב"ם
Rambam try to give like- they don't really say anything different, they
just try to give a little bit better insight into why it
might be called two animals. So תוספות Tosafos says because the פסוק
pasuk says you can eat this and you can be טמא tamei
when you eat this animal and it says כאשר יאכל ka'asher yechal
Just like you would eat the deer and the איל, ayal, whatever
an איל ayal is, the ibex I guess. Anyway, so since the
תורה, Torah, here let me take a look, תוספות Tosfos quotes here,
yeah, כצבי וכאיל. katzvi vecha'ayal. So since the תורה Torah describes this
particular animal as a צבי tzvi and an איל, ayal, it's like
a צבי tzvi and it's like an איל, ayal, the תורה Torah
is saying this has a double identity of two separate animals mixed
together. The רמב"ם Rambam also says that's because the תורה Torah sort
of describes it here, let me see if I have the רמב"ם
Rambam's position here. I mean, it's a crazy idea. If
the רשב"ם Rashbam says דבר תמה הוא. davar teima hu. The רמב"ם
Rambam says, hold on, where is the רמב"ם? Rambam? The רמב"ם Rambam
says, ט' י"א, tes yud aleph, here he says, the reason it's
considered two animals is he says, "ואם
כל בהמה טמאה אשר לא יקריבו ממנו קרבן להשם". ve'im kol behema
tmeia asher lo yakrivu mimenu korban la-Hashem. So the תורה Torah says
a non-kosher animal that you can't bring as a קרבן. korban. So
he says, well this is an animal that you could have brought
as a קרבן korban that you can't anymore bring as a קרבן,
korban, and the תורה Torah therefore by calling, by using the phrase
בהמה טמאה, behema tmeia, is saying that this is like it's a
non-kosher animal. So now it's like a non-kosher animal and a kosher
animal mixed together and therefore, if you just even have it draw
a load, it's like you're bringing, you're having two separate animals draw
a load. It's pretty crazy. I mean, it's one thing to say
if you crossbreed, if you breed it at least with another animal,
we look at it as two separate animals, but to say the
one animal itself and just by having that one animal draw a
load you're עובר over on the prohibition of כלאים, kilayim, it's pretty
wild. Why wouldn't we say that if you actually made a crossbred
animal, let's say you made a mule, which is like a donkey
and a horse, right? And then I took a mule, which is
literally two, a crossbred animal, and I use a mule, why aren't
I being עובר over on כלאים? kilayim? No, it's totally מותר mutar
to use a mule. But this, you're עובר over on כלאים, kilayim,
it's pretty wild. All right, anyway, moving on. Don't ask me to
explain it, if everybody else says this דבר תמה, davar teima, I'm
certainly not going to say otherwise. Okay, next משנה. mishna. כמה מלקין?
kama malkin? Now we get to the actual administration of the lashes.
How do you give lashes or how many do you give? ארבעים
חסר אחת. arba'im chaser achat.
Although the תורה Torah says 40, "ארבעים יכנו לא יוסיף", arba'im yakenu
lo yosif, we say it means 39. שנאמר במספר ארבעים. shene'emar bemispar
arba'im. So it says the, what's the פסוק? pasuk? It says "כדי
רשעתו במספר", kdei rish'ato bemispar, you should give him lashes according to
the right number, "ארבעים יכנו לא יוסיף". arba'im yakenu lo yosif. Okay,
so they're separate פסוקים. psukim. Okay, so somehow the word במספר ארבעים
bemispar arba'im is read to mean like up to the number of
40 but not up to a full 40. It says
"כדי רשעתו במספר" kdei rish'ato bemispar according to his wickedness in the
right amount, "ארבעים יכנו לא יוסיף".
arba'im yakenu
lo yosif. Okay, so we read במספר ארבעים bemispar arba'im somehow means
like up to the number 40, which means somehow 39. Okay, מניין
שהוא סמוך למניין
שהוא סמוך לארבעים, minayin shehu samuch leminyan shehu samuch le'arba'im, a number
that approximates or that gets right up to 40. רבי יהודה אומר
ארבעים שלמות הוא לוקה. Rabbi Yehuda omer arba'im shleimot hu lokei. No,
a full 40. והיכן הוא לוקה היתרה? ve'heichan hu lokei hayeteira? Where
does he give the 40th lash? Because he doesn't disagree to the
idea that basically you divide it into three, into sets of three,
and we'll talk about like one set, one is in front and
two are on his back. Okay, so if they're divided into sets
of three, where does he give the 40th lash? בין כתיפיו, bein
kteifav, between the shoulder blades. All right, אין אומדין אותו אלא במקום
ראוי להשתלש. ein omdin oto ela bemakom ra'ui lehishtaleish. You only give
him, you assess how much he can withstand. Now that's also not
in the תורה. Torah. The תורה Torah sounds like you always give
40. But you know, once we say 39, once we've sort of
broken the number 40, so now it's like somewhat like now we
can sort of negotiate, right? Now we can sort of say really
we assess how much the person can take and if he can't
take the full 40, we give him a different number. But whatever
number we give him, it has to be divisible by three because
you divide the lashes into three. אמדוהו לקבל ארבעים ולקה מקצת. amduhu
lekabel arba'im velaka miktzat. Now, let's say you assessed that he could
withstand the full 40 or 39 and you started giving him lashes
ואמדו שאין יכול לקבל ארבעים ve'amdu she'ein yachol lekabel arba'im and then
you realize like whoa, you know what, he's not going to be
able to take the full amount. We thought he could take 39,
we started giving him lashes, we see the effect that it's having
on him, we think now he can only take 21. Okay, פטור.
patur. So actually, rather than just readjusting down and doing 21, you
actually let him go free completely because what you say is it
looks like our number, you really, we only have the one number
we assessed, we said 39. Now we see we can't give you
the 39. If we can't give you the 39, you go free.
You got the idea? Meaning we don't get to change the number,
and since we can no longer give that number, we're going to
have to let you go free. Okay, אמדו לקבל שמונה עשרה. amdu
l'kabel shmoneh esrei.
Let's say he said 18, okay? ומשלקה אמדו שיכול לקבל ארבעים. u-mishelaka
amdu she-yachol l'kabel arba'im. And then we started giving you lashes and
we saw you were a lot stronger than we thought. פטור. patur.
You still don't get 40, you still only get the 18. We're
stuck with the number we've got. So once we start giving lashes,
if it's before we began giving the lashes, the implication in the
mishnah, which the Gemara will discuss, is that you're able to reassess
before the process begins. Okay? But once the process begins, we're locked
into our number. So we can't add to it even if you
could have withstood more, it becomes obvious. And if you can't take
the full number, then we can't give you less, so we have
to let you go free. All right? But that's only once the
process began. Presumably we can reassess before the process. Let's take a
look at the Gemara.
מאי טעמא? ma'e ta'ama?
What's the reason that we say it means 39? אי כתיב ארבעים
במספר, i-ksiv arba'im b'mispar,
40 in number, הוי אמינא ארבעים במניינא, havy amina arba'im b'minyana, the
full 40. השתא דכתיב במספר ארבעים, hasha d'ksiv b'mispar arba'im, within the
number 40. I don't really get the particular grammar or what its
particular point, the particular significance of reading it this way. So מניין
שסוכם את הארבעים, minyan she-shocheim et ha-arba'im, a number that leads up
to 40, that's right up to 40. Okay, so that's how we
get 39. אמר רבא, amar Rava, says Rava,
כמה טפשאי שאר אינשי. kama tishai shei inshi. How stupid are other
people, I guess like
the עמי הארץ ammei ha-aretz or whatever, דקיימי מקמי ספר תורה. de-kaimi
mikmei Sefer Torah. When a Sefer Torah comes into the room, everybody
stands up. ולא קיימי מקמי גברא רבא. v'lo kaimi mikmei gavra raba.
But they don't stand up when a great Torah sage enters the
room. Now why is that stupid? Because דאילו בספר תורה כתיב ארבעים
ואתו רבנן בצרו חדא. de-illu b'Sefer Torah ksiv arba'im v'asu rabanan batru
chada.
Because I'll just prove to you the Torah sage is greater than
the Torah. The Torah says 40 and the rabbis come along and
they say no, we'll take one away, we'll say only 39. And
who gets to have the final word? The rabbis. Okay? So it's
like there's the Constitution and there's the Supreme Court. At the end
of the day, who gets to determine what's written in the Constitution?
Not the framers of the Constitution, not the document itself, but the
Supreme Court. They're the ones with the real authority. So the Torah
says 40, but at the end of the day, we're not biblical
Jews, we're rabbinic Jews. So it's ultimately, so if you want to
know whose authority really dictates in terms of what
the Torah means, it's very interesting, the self-awareness of their creativity
and how their interpretation
impacts the פשט pshat reading of the verse and then ultimately that
what they interpreted becomes authoritative. It is really interesting question, why do
they feel that an explicit number 40 they were motivated to read
it as
39? You can't say like הלכה למשה מסיני, halacha l'Moshe mi-Sinai, רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda reads it as 40. So I think that this
maybe is a little bit of a hint to why that was.
Because as I was sort of saying in the mishnah, the fact
that where's this idea that we can also make a lower number,
that we assess whether you can withstand it or we can make
a lower number. It's like once I've proven that 40 is not
sacrosanct, once sort of we've gone down, once I say no, it's
not 40, it's 39, it basically has already demonstrated that we the
rabbis get to determine how much the amount is. I think it's
really the point that Rava is making. Oh, we're determining that the
40 means 39. Once we're saying that 40 means 39, we can
also say that if you can't withstand 39, it means 18 or
it means 21 or it means, so I think it gives, it
shows our power to determine what the meaning is. Okay, so now
let's keep on going. רבי יהודה אומר ארבעים שלמות, Rabbi Yehuda omer
arba'im shleimot, 40. אמר רבי יצחק, amar Rabbi Yitzchak, says Rabbi Yitzchak,
מאי טעמא דרבי יהודה? ma'e ta'ama de-Rabbi Yehuda? What's his reasoning? דכתיב
מה המכות האלה בין ידיך. d'ksiv mah makkot ha-eleh bein yadecha. What
are these lashes between your hands? And so that means he's reading
between the shoulder blades and that's where he reads that you get
the 40. The actual פשט pshat of that פסוק pasuk is that
these false prophets, in the future people will deny that they were
being false prophets and that they were being prophets, once in the
messianic period. So people will say, well then why are your hands
lashed, why are there
bruises on your hands? Because presumably the false prophets would get into
some frenzy when they were prophesying and it would lead to bruises
on their hands and they would try to
disavow their past. So they would say, oh, what are those bruises
doing? אשר הכיתי בית מאהבי. asher hikaiti beis m'ahavai. I was just,
I got beaten up at my friend's house or something. So that's
the פשט pshat of the פסוק, pasuk, that they're just trying to
disavow their past as being false prophets. But anyway, for us we're
reading it that there's lashes between the hand, which is being read
as between the shoulder blades. Okay, ורבנן, v'rabanan, and the rabbis say
ההוא בתינוקות של בית רבן, ahu b'tinokot shel beis raban, דכתיב. d'ksiv.
That's not talking about court-administered lashes, that's talking about like some type
of way that kids get hit in school. Okay, we've had that
once before, corporal punishment of children and so on. All righty. אינו
לוקה אלא במעמד שלשה. eino lokeh ela b'ma'amad shlosha. אין עושין מילוי
במכת הראויות. Ein osin milluy be-makkas hara'uyos. So now the משנה Mishnah
says that once the process began we can't change the number. So
if you can't stand the full number you get off the hook
and if you can stand more אין עושין מילוי במכת הראויות. Ein
osin milluy be-makkas hara'uyos. So now the משנה Mishnah says that once
the process began we can't change the number. So if you can't
stand the full number you get off the hook and if you
can stand more we can't give you more. But before the process
began it sounds like we get to revise it, we get to
reassess. So the גמרא Gemara says, it said לקה אין לא לקה
לא, laka in, lo laka lo, only once the lashes began do
we not get to reassess, but without that we
do. ורמינהו, U-raminhu, I'll ask you, we have a ברייתא braisa that
seems to say it doesn't matter. אמדוהו לקבל ארבעים, Amduhu lekabel arbaim,
they assessed for forty, וחזרו ואמדו שאינו יכול לקבל ארבעים, ve-hazru ve-amdu
she-eino yachol lekabel arbaim, and then they said he couldn't accept it,
פטור, patur, he's exempt. It sounds like once we made the assessment
we're stuck with it even if the process didn't begin. So if
we said forty, even before the process began, now we see you
can't take forty, you're totally off the hook. אמדוהו לקבל שמונה עשרה,
Amduhu lekabel shmoneh esreh, we said eighteen, וחזרו ואמדו שיכול לקבל ארבעים,
ve-hazru ve-amdu she-yachol lekabel arbaim, and now we say oh you know
what we made a mistake, you really can take more, so it
sounds like nevertheless we're stuck with eighteen because even before the process
began פטור, patur, you're exempt. That actually does sound like you might
get off completely but anyway, either way this ברייתא braisa sounds like
we don't get to reassess even before the process began and our
משנה Mishnah sounds like we don't get to reassess only once the
lashes began. So אמר רב ששת, Amar Rav Sheshes, says Rav Sheshes,
לא קשיא, lo kashya, it's not difficult. הא דאמדוהו ליומיה הא דאמדוהו
למחר ליומא אחרא. Ha de-amduhu le-yomei, ha de-amduhu le-machar le-yoma achara. It's
whether was the assessment for the day or was it for a
different day. Now huh like how does that matter? So there's like
it's very there's a רש"י, Rashi, רב"ן, Rivan, and a תוספות Tosafos
and nobody nobody has like a clean explanation. But the basic sort
of way the רב"ן Rivan explains it is is that if we
assessed somebody, I mean here's one explanation, we assessed him today that
he can go ahead and accept a certain actually no, now that
I'm trying to say it out loud it doesn't make sense. Anyway,
he says something
like this. We if before the
let me try it this way. If before the process began we
realize we made a mistake, okay since the assessment was for today
and we realize we made a mistake today, then since the process
didn't begin we can sort of say okay the initial decision was
just clearly a mistake you know and so on. It's all happening
in the same day. It's like a תוך כדי דיבור. toch k'dei
dibbur. So as long as the process didn't begin we're able to
reassess. So that idea that you can reassess before the process began
that's when it was all happening on the same day. Okay but
if we decide we're going to give you lashes tomorrow and we're
going to say that we have assessed you to say that like
you know tomorrow we know that you're of good health and whatever
and we'll assess that tomorrow you'll be able to receive x amount
of lashes and then it comes tomorrow and we want to reassess
okay then it says like then you can't say it was a
mistake and then you're locked into your original assessment. I don't really
get that at all. Like tomorrow you might be in a different
state of health right? So all the more reason to be able
to say tomorrow we should be able to reassess. It's I don't
know like I know that I mean whatever I could tell you
what he says, it is what he said, but like you know
nobody comes up with a clean explanation about this but his basic
his point is is that if it's on the same day we
get an opportunity to then we can reassess before the process began
because we can say we made a mistake. But if it's on
a different day somehow because we're making an assessment for long term
and we're meant taking we know we're only going to give you
lashes tomorrow and we're making the assessment today for tomorrow then there's
no way we can say it was a mistake and we don't
get to reassess and we're stuck with our original assessment. I don't
really get it. Okay but anyway let's just read the next משנה,
Mishnah, the גמרא, Gemara, I'm sorry that I did not have a
better explanation for that but I did not see a better explanation
in the ירושלמי. Yerushalmi. עבר עבירה שיש בה שני לאוין, Avar aveira
she-yesh bah shenei lavin, we're just going to read the next quick
משנה Mishnah and גמרא. Gemara.
אמדוהו אומד אחד לוקה ופטור. Amduhu omed echad lokeh u-fatur. So somebody
did two sins. Okay now it sounds like it's one thing not
two separate sins, it sounds like it's the previous משנה, Mishnah, one
act that has two transgressions like he did this plowing thing. Okay
and therefore so somebody went ahead and they plowed with כלאים kilayim
on שמיטה Shmita okay or on יום טוב. Yom Tov. So how
many
so that's that's he gets two he should get two sets of
lashes okay but this guy what do we do? Do we sort
of say let's say this guy can only withstand you know thirty-nine
lashes at a time? Do we say okay you did one act
two sets of lashes, come today we'll give you set number one,
heal up, come back next week we'll give you set number two?
That's one way of saying it. Another way of saying it is
like you did one act and you deserve you know seventy seventy-eight
lashes, you can only accept thirty-nine so we'll give you thirty-nine and
that'll be the total amount of lashes you get for the two
עבירות. aveiros. You understand like the two different ways of looking at
it? If it was two separate acts it would seem clearly those
are two separate court cases come on different days and each one
will be treated separately. But if it's one act with two עבירות
aveiros with two transgressions do we view it as you deserve seventy-eight,
you can accept... 35 or whatever 36, excuse me, or 42 or
whatever it is and that'll be the total you get out of
the 78 because you can't withstand the full 78. Or do we
say no, we'll give you set number one now and come back
tomorrow and we'll give you set number two. Okay, so the משנה
Mishnah says אמדוהו אומד אחד, amduhu omed echad, so it depends what
בית דין Beis Din chose to do. If they made one assessment
and they sort of bundled it together, לוקה ופטור, lokei upatur, he
gets the amount of lashes he can withstand, maybe it's 39, maybe
it's 36, maybe it's 42, and that's the total amount of lashes
he gets for the 78 that he deserves for the two, for
the double transgression he did.
Wait, 42 at one time? Because doesn't...
No, but it's for a double transgression.
No, I know, but still isn't there this prohibition of לא יוסיף?
lo yosif? So we would conceptualize it as the first 39 are
for transgression one, the next three are for transgression two, or maybe
we'd conceptualize it as 21 and 21.
But it's still going to be that aspect of demeaning the person,
right?
Right, but somehow we're seeing that that's per like עבירה, aveira, you
know? But I hear your question. Okay, ואם לאו לוקה משתפה וחוזר
ולוקה. ve'im lav lokei mishtappe vechozer velokei. If they decide to do
two separate assessments, so he gets whatever he can withstand today, and
that's for עבירה aveira number one. And then he heals up and
comes back for עבירה aveira number two. So like who gets to
decide which בית דין Beis Din does? Everybody would want בית דין
Beis Din to do the first version rather than the second version,
right? It's like when you get 10 life sentences, do you serve
them consecutively or whatever, you know what I'm saying? You always want
it to be done all at once, right? Anyway the גמרא Gemara
says ותניא אין אומדים אומד אחד בשני לאוין. vetanya ein omdin omed
echad bishnei lavin. But one minute, we have a ברייתא Beraisa that
says you don't, you always have to treat them separate. You don't
get to do one assessment for two. אמר רב ששת לא קשיא,
amar Rav Sheshet la kashya, it's not difficult. הא דאמדוהו לארבעין וחדא
והא דאמדוהו לארבעין ותרתי. ha de'amduhu le'arba'in vechada veha de'amduhu le'arba'in vetarti.
He says like this: If we assess that you can accept up
through 41, right? Because up through 41, you're not yet, meaning 39
is for עבירה aveira number one, to have any amount that would
count as a threesome for עבירה aveira number two, we'd have to
bump you up to 42. Right? You see that, right? 39 plus
three is 42. So any if you can accept can't accept more
than 41, then we say we can only punish you right now
for עבירה aveira number one. Because the only way we could conceptualize
it as punishing you for עבירה aveira number two is if we
could give you 42 lashes or more. If you can withstand 42
or more, then we'll give you 42 today and we'll say 39
is for עבירה aveira number one, three is for עבירה aveira number
two. But if we only gave you 39 or 36 or you
know or whatever or 33, then we can't say some of those
are for עבירה aveira number one and some are for עבירה aveira
number two. Right? Since it's 39 or less, they have to all
be for עבירה aveira number one. Only once עבירה aveira number one
has its full amount can we say the extras for עבירה aveira
number two. Okay, so basically it says like this: If the person
today can't accept
42 or more, then we can only punish him today for עבירה
aveira number one and come back tomorrow for עבירה aveira number two.
If he can accept 42 or more, then it sounds like it's
at the discretion of the court. They can decide to say we're
going to bundle it up and give you today 42 or 45
or whatever and punish you for עבירה aveira one and two, or
they're going to say we're going to punish you today for עבירה
aveira number one, heal up, come back tomorrow for עבירה aveira number
two and you'll wind up getting a lot more lashes if they
divide it between two days than if they bundled it up. But
if they're able to do 42 or more, they have the option
of bundling it together. Okay, if the person can withstand that amount
of lashes.
All right, we will pick up with this tomorrow.